<?xml version="1.0"?>
<blog>

    <post>
        <title>you are not a gadget - what is a person?</title>
        <date>2015-04-29 15:43:46</date>
        <tag1>AI</tag1>
        <tag2>ethics</tag2>
        <tag3>books</tag3>
        <tag4></tag4>
        <summary>
            Jason Lanier's book describes how recent developments in our culture
            and it's use of social networks, cloud computing and the internet are
            eroding our sense of person and supressing individual expression.
        </summary>

        <contents><![CDATA[
        <p>Jason Lanier is a philosopher and computer scientist connected with UC
        Berkeley. His book <a href="http://www.penguin.co.uk/books/you-are-not-a-gadget/9780141049113/">You are not a gadget</a>
        is part apocalyptic vision and part a call to arms. In
        the first chapter he talks about how our sense of person and of what it
        means to be human is gradually being eroded. Here are some quotes that
        particularly stood out for me. (some are partially edited - I hope he doesn't
        mind)</p>

        <p><em>"The turing test cuts both ways. You can't tell if a machine has got smarter
        or if you've just lowered your own standards of intelligence to such a degree
        that the machine seems smart... People degrade themselves in order to make machines
        seem smart all the time... We ask teachers to teach to standardized tests so a student
        will look good to an algorithm. We have repeatedly demonstrated our species' bottomless
        ability to lower our standards to make information technology look good."</em></p>

        <p><em>"What computerized analysis of the country's school tests has done
        to education is exactly what Facebook has done to friendships. In both cases,
        life is turned into a database. Both degradations are based on the same
        philosophical mistake, which is a belief that computers can represent human thought
        or human relationships. These are things that computers cannot currently do."</em></p>

        <p><em>"Something like missionary reductionism has happened to the internet with
        the rise of web 2.0. Individual web pages as they first appeared in the early 1990s
        had the flavor of personhood. MySpace preserved some of that flavor, though a process
        of regularized formatting had begun. Facebook went further, organizing people into
        multiple-choice identities, while Wikipedia seeks to erase point of view entirely.
        If a church or government were doing these things, it would feel authoritarian...
        People will accept ideas presented in technological form that would be abhorrent in
        any other form."</em></p>

        ]]></contents>

    </post>

</blog>