<?xml version="1.0"?>
<blog>

    <post>
        <title>you are not a gadget - flatness</title>
        <date>2015-05-06 16:00:46</date>
        <tag1>AI</tag1>
        <tag2>ethics</tag2>
        <tag3>books</tag3>
        <tag4></tag4>
        <summary>
            Jaron Lanier's book describes how recent developments in our culture
            and it's use of social networks, cloud computing and the internet are
            eroding our sense of person and supressing individual expression.
        </summary>

        <contents><![CDATA[
        <p>Jaron Lanier is a philosopher and computer scientist connected with UC
        Berkeley. His book <a href="http://www.penguin.co.uk/books/you-are-not-a-gadget/9780141049113/">You are not a gadget</a>
        is part apocalyptic vision and part a call to arms. In
        the third chapter, he talks about how the flatness encouraged in internet design
        and the attitudes and culture of parts of the open source movement
         encourages blandness and meaninglessness. Here are some quotes that
        particularly stood out for me. (some are partially edited - I hope he doesn't
        mind)</p>

        <p><em>"Let's suppose that back in the 1980s I had said, 'In a quarter century
        when the digital revolution has made great advances and progress and computer
        chips are millions of times faster than they are now, humanity will finally
        win a prize of being able to write a new encyclopedia and a new version of
        UNIX!' It would have sounded utterly pathetic."</em></p>

        <p><em>"Some of the youngest, brightest minds have been trapped in a 1970s
        intellectual framework because they are hypnotized into accepting old
        software designs as if they were facts of nature. Linux is a superbly polished copy
        of an antique - shinier than the original perhaps, but still defined by
        it... The politically correct dogma that holds that open source is automatically
        the best path to creativity and innovation is not borne out by the facts."</em></p>

        ]]></contents>

    </post>

</blog>